Hello!  Welcome back to Lam Rim.
Today we will review the entire course.  It
's good for me.  I would like to do a review for myself.
This format where you participate in separate episodes
and at different times
can make you lose the structure of the entire teaching.  I
thought it would be nice if today we started
from the beginning and went through the structure of the
entire Lam Rim teaching that we have been through.  I'm going to
go through all the ideas based on IDIMs, the IDea IMaginilor,
which we use to teach ACI teachers.
ACI teachers
should be able to look at one of these images
and identify the idea behind it.
Tim, how many images did I say there would be?   A thousand or so?  How
many?
500 or something like that.  It's easy to give an exam,
to examine someone based on images alone.  We're just showing you these pictures
.
So I challenge you that during this review
when I show you an image I'm going to
give you a second to see if you
remember what that image was about.
And so we will do a good review
of the entire course we took.  Okay.  Let's begin...
First photo, Mr.  The seats.
This image should remind you
that we are in the middle of practices
for people with average motivation.
And that they are trying to achieve nirvana.
They are trying to get out of the wheel of life, out of all their personal suffering.
Here the Buddha taught the three trainings
that will help you reach personal nirvana.
The third training is understanding emptiness, understanding PIX.
The second training is meditation.
On a deep level, these two practices can only be done in a quiet place,
at certain times of the day, when you are truly focused while sitting on the meditation cushion.
On a deep level, these two need to be done
at special times of the day.
But this, the foundation for the two, which is to be good to other people,
[which] you can call morality, you
can call it an ethical way of life,
but ultimately it is [the idea] of being good to other people.
This is the foundation
that is always at our fingertips throughout the day.
This is one of the three great trainings of Buddhism,
designed to help us achieve nirvana.
And it's at our fingertips all day long.
In this image you
can see Seiji helping Geshe Michael with the computer,
which is one of the nicest things young people can do for the elderly.
Next picture... See if you remember what this picture was about?  Did
you guess?
This lady is calculating her taxes.  What does it mean that she is doing in this Lam Rim system?  It
makes her...
...a Dharma Master.   When I say Dharma Master, or Tantric Master,
I know what image you have in your mind:
a great lama on a throne wearing a big yellow hat.
Maybe he's ringing a bell and beating a small drum and it's...
And you think, "This is a Dharma Master. This is a real Dharma Master."
Or you think of the old picture of Nagarjuna.
And he is mystical in every way.
In Lam Rim I learned
that a simple woman
who has two children, is married,
is a Dharma Master.  She is a true Dharma Master.
Pabongka Rinpoche said, “Do not think that a Dharma Master must sit on a throne
reciting a tantric ritual.”
What is this lady doing?
He pays his taxes on time.
Calculating taxes correctly is really difficult in my country [USA].  It
could take weeks to calculate your taxes,
to calculate them carefully,
to calculate them properly,
to pay every penny you should pay.
This makes her...
She has the first of the extraordinary trainings of a good person,
she has kindness towards other people.  This is what
a true Dharma Master does.
Forget [about] those images you have of lots of lamas with big hats on their heads,
and bells ringing.  That's easy.
Anyone can do this.
Being nice to people is difficult [especially in difficult, crisis situations].
Maintaining your morality, maintaining your ethics
is also difficult.
Next.  I'll give you
a moment.  Do you remember what it's about?  The
quote from Lam Rim was @TSUL KHRIMS LDAN PA'I DGE SLONG 'OD DANG LDAN.
A person who truly keeps their vows,
who truly keeps the Buddhist guidelines, especially the 10 precepts,
shines, really shines.
A person who makes a healthy, modest, constant effort to keep their commitments,
to stick to the ten good deeds,
and to be good to other people.
[She] has a kind of peaceful look on her face, she's
glowing.
When he walks into a room, you know it.
Everyone starts to feel better, like Tim and Seiji.
This is a light of the world.
Buddha said, "Those people are the light of the world."
There is a Christian expression:
"Don't put a candle under a bushel, let the world see your happy face."
And this is a true guiding light for the entire world.
Next image IDIM#4
This is a rock that I climbed with my partner Veronica, for her birthday, during this Lam Rim.
We were talking about sunset, for which the Tibetan word is @NUB PA.
It is also the word for west, because the sun sets in the west.
@NUB PA means
sunset and that is a very sad verb.
This is a very sad idea in dharma.
The most famous place is at the end of the book Abhidharmakosha - the Treasury of Higher Wisdom.
"The Treasury of Higher Wisdom" is written by Master Vasabhandu.  And he says:
"The sun of Dharma, the light of Dharma, will set in this world."
"We will lose the light of Dharma in this world."  "This world will go into darkness."
"After a certain period of time, the
Buddha's teachings will disappear in this world."
"They will first disappear from people's minds, but they will still be in libraries."
Those books are still in libraries.  Probably libraries that John Brady hasn't found yet.
"And then later, they will disappear from libraries and then they will be taken away."  I
put the image here because Pabongka Rinpoche pointed out a special idea.  He said,
"If you cannot keep your commitments, if you cannot behave nicely towards other people,
then we can say that the Dharma has left this world."
The light of Dharma has left this world within you.
The sun has set in your own chest,
which would be a very sad thing if we did not keep our vows.  The
next picture.
We called this retreat "Love in the Time of Virus."
The point is that if during a very difficult time in the world, you
keep your commitments,
you're good to other people,
when things are scary and scary and the virus is spreading, we
don't know where, we don't know how, and we do
n't know how many people are going to die.
If in those difficult times you do something good towards other people,
it is much, much more powerful.
If you remember, he mentioned a 5-star Buddha paradise,
which is like a perfect place.
It's easy to be a good person, everyone there is a good person.  That's
not a big achievement.                                            It's no big deal.
And the seed is not that strong --
to be nice in a group of nice people.
To be good when people attack you, when people are afraid,
when people are not good to each other, and to be the only person
who comes forward and gives things away during a difficult time -
then that is an extremely pure person.
This is powerful karma.  It's incredible karma, much stronger.
I think the coming of this virus is a very good moment, and
it's a very good chance for all of us to show:
- Are we really true Buddhists?   Are we really practicing the bodhisattva path?
Can we help others even when things are very difficult?  The
next picture.  This one
is hard to remember, I'm having trouble remembering what it's about.  I'm going to
give you some extra time to think about what this image represents.
Pabongka Rinpoche quotes a few books
with a very, very common ending for different books.  The
famous quote he quoted is @BLO BZANG RGYAL BA'I BSTAN PA... CIG
May the teachings of the victorious
Lobsang Drakpa, Je Tsongkapa
spread throughout this world.  You're
thinking we need to go online
and translate this Lam Rim into multiple languages.  We
must try to spread the good word to as many people as possible.
This is the end of the prayer and we should exit this Lam Rim session or this video.
And we should share the Dharma with other people.  We
should spread Dharma in the world.
In this part of Lam Rim, Pabongka Rinpoche said,
“The place where you should spread the Dharma is here, in your heart.”
Don't think that spreading the Dharma means translating videos
into multiple languages ​​or anything like that.  This is a very important spread of the Dharma.
But, he says, "If you spread Dharma within your heart,
then of course it will spread outside of you because the world comes from your heart."
From the heart chakra, actually.
Next image #7
Try to remember what this image was about.  I'll leave you for a second.
This is a favorite topic of mine:
having a personal relationship with another person, like these two people have.
In my opinion and in tantra, it is one of the happiest things that can happen to you.
It's one of the greatest things that can happen to you.
Anyone can tell you the reason why the whole world is looking for a partner.
The reason is that it makes people happy.
It is one of the greatest joys when things go well.
It's one of the greatest joys you can have, but
we both know that when it doesn't go well,
it's one of the greatest misfortunes in life.
Why is this relevant to this course here?
If your morality is good,
it is the happiest thing in your life.
And if you violate your morality, the same thing will make you unhappy.
It's like having a man or woman you like who is your partner,
and the same person who makes you completely happy
can also make you completely unhappy.
So in this case, the vinaya, your personal practice of being good to others,
your good behavior, is compared to a partner
who can be the best thing in your life
or the worst thing in your life - the same person.
Next IDIM #8
That was a complicated one.  Can you remember?  I'm going to
take a sip of my green drink.
Thank you, Vimala.
This actually represents breaking your commitments.
Pulling out a weed represents breaking your commitments.
Why is destroying this plant a breach of commitment?
If you're a gardener, you know you should pull a weed out of the ground
before the seeds ripen.
If you wait until the seeds are ready to fall,
and then pull the plant out of the ground,
you will scatter about a thousand seeds.
Next month or next year you'll get thousands of weeds growing.
So, you will need to attack these weeds early.
This refers to a very radical statement
that the Buddha made:
@DGE SLONG DAG SROG DANG BRAL ZHING SHI BA NI BLA'I
It says that it is better to die
than to break your vows.  Why?
When you break your vows
you set in motion seeds
that will continue to fall for many lifetimes.
If you die, you destroy a single mind-body entity.
If you die, you destroy only one very useful temple,
a physical temple and a mind.  You lost one life.
But if you break your vows,
you lose more mind-body ensembles.  You are
destroying your body and mind for many lifetimes.
And you have set in motion seeds
that will destroy many lives.
Buddha said, "It is better to die than to break your vows," and he
wasn't being metaphorical.  He was speaking literally
when he said that.  Better to die than to break your commitments.
There is a joke in Lam Rim.
We make a vow to never give up bodhichitta even at the cost of our lives.
There is a famous statement, our whole lives we wait
to be thrown in jail
by certain bad people.
They come with a knife and say, "Give up your bodhisattva vows or die today."
We will tell [them]:
"I choose to die."  And they kill us
.
I think we've all been waiting for this since we took that oath.
We're waiting for these guys with knives to show up and threaten us.
But actually we're the guys with the knives.  We threaten our bodhisattva vows every day.  We
must make this decision every day when we decide whether or not to keep our vows carefully.
It's hard to find the guys who will throw you in jail and say,
"I'll kill you if you don't give up your bodhisattva vows."  The
next picture.
See if you remember.  I'll give you a minute to try to remember.
This was a reference....
we have the Mixed Nuts translation team
and we were translating an old vinaya text.
The vows of monks, the vows of nuns.
They were talking about the vow, the custom that you shouldn't...
...When you become a monk or nun you're given robes, they
give you a little Buddhist statue,
and they give you a strainer.
In ancient India you had to carry this strainer with you.
When drinking water from a stream you
should strain the water first to make sure you don't kill any small insects.
I mentioned a famous custom in the vinaya,
if two monks go down to the water,
down to the stream to get water,
then they should choose the most benevolent monk to check the water.
Don't choose the one who doesn't care about insects.  Find a guy who loves bugs
and have him check the water because he'll be more careful.
What's the idea?
We talked about a type of ecological vow,
where monks and nuns are not supposed to even pull the leaves of
a plant, because they are shelter for small creatures.
This means - to respect even very small vows,
take them very seriously, because the results multiply exponentially.
Then, it's important to keep your morality at a very subtle level,
at a very fine level, and don't analyze them.
If I were to write the bodhisattva vows, I
would write an additional bodhisattva vow about
not analyzing your bodhisattva vows.  There
's nothing more irritating than
a person informing you that they're honoring their vows and that's why they
have to be insensitive today.
Keep your vows in a pleasant way.  Keep them being happy.  Don't exaggerate.
Don't bother other people with your vows because vows are not meant to bother other people.
Keep vows small, keep them quiet.  Keep them to yourself, don't advertise them.
There is a saying in Islam... Let the left hand not know what the right hand is doing.
That means not advertising your vows.  Keep them quiet.
Keep them at a very fine level.  The
next picture.
Here is the idea that being kind to others
is like planting a tree.
Today I went to the Peach Tree Cafe
to check something out.
Stanley, Allison, and I planted a peach tree there
when we first started the morning show, "The Peach Tree."
And I want to tell you that three peaches came out this week.
And now we have peaches.
That means taking care of basic practices.
Take care of your roots and plant beautiful karma
by keeping your vows and being kind to others.
And this will turn into a tree.
And that peach tree that I planted
about five months ago is
already bearing a lot of fruit.
If you hadn't taken care of it when it was small [the tree], you would have nothing [now].
If you take care of the foundation of your Buddhist practice,
which is being kind to other people,
then the fruits will be thousands and thousands and thousands.
[The result] will come, it will grow
...it will turn into a tree
that will bear peaches every year and you will have fruit for many years.
Preserve... protect...
This child carefully protects the shoot.
Protect your morality.  [Keep your morals]
Next picture.
If I remember correctly, there were four conditions
that could cause you to break your commitments.
If you've taken your bodhisattva vows
or you've taken your pratimoksha vinaya vows,
or even if you've taken your tantric Diamond Way vows
... I think there were four... ...that Pabongka Rinpoche reviewed... maybe more....
However, there are certain conditions
that can "help" you break your vows.
If you want to break your vows, there are a few ways to do it.  The
first way
is to not know the vows
and that's a good way to break them.  If you want to break them,
then don't study them and
one of the things that bothers me... I have a lot of things that annoy me about the Dharma,
is teachers who give initiations, huge initiations,
and they don't explain to the people they're initiating
that they've just taken vows.
There are hundreds of vows you take when you receive an initiation,
and you will [certainly] break them if you don't know them.
It is the teacher's responsibility to
prepare you regarding the vows before giving you an initiation.
If they don't offer to train me, [I] wouldn't accept an initiation from them.
The best way to break your vows, the first way, is to not know them.
Read the recipe before you start cooking.
That's what Veronica tells me every time I cook.  The
next picture.
There's a lady who says, "Hey, it's no big deal."
That vow about cutting down green plants without saying a prayer,
seriously, that's a bit of an exaggeration.  It's a bit too much, it's not that important.
There are just a few insects
that might use that leaf from time to time as a roof.  It's no
big deal.
The second great way to break your vows
is to have this attitude.
"Oh, this oath is not that important, I keep the big ones."
Next.
If we have a klesha, meaning if we have some kind of negativity
running through our mind, that's a very good way to break your vows.
Being irritated by someone else or
being obsessed with purchasing something or money or
being addicted to watching Netflix at night.
...By the way, it's not wrong to watch Netflix [movies], I'm talking about
hurting someone else because you want to get home and watch Netflix.  That's a problem.
This is called gang warfare.
What is the story about?
Always go after the biggest guy on the opposing side.
Find out who the leader of the other side is,
and don't talk, don't negotiate, don't yell at each other,
just go up to him and hit him in the head.
And then all the others [his colleagues] will give up.
Identify your biggest bad habit,
and go for it first.  That's how you take your vows.
Next.
...By the way, at my age, I wo
n't tell you how old I am,
but this whole young love thing
is so ridiculous from the perspective of my age.
I can say it from experience, because I had it.
This...
"Oh, she's the most beautiful woman in the world."
"He's the most handsome guy in the world."
First of all, my older brother
said the funniest thing.  He said, "Do you like that girl?"  I said, "Yes."  He
said, "Do you want to spend your life with her?"  I said, "Yes."
He said, "First look at her mother."
"Look at what her mother looks like." I said [her] mother looks terrible.  She's overweight, looks tired, and looks terrible.
And he said to me, "Well, what do you think he looked like when he was young?"
Think about this.
If you are attached to a person's appearance,
or to something physical, or to something that is not very important about a person,
that appearance will change and you will see them get sick, you
will see them get old, you will see them have diarrhea and vomit.
If you're not lucky, at some point you'll see his entrails or on the operating table.  Do
n't fool yourself into thinking
that it's worth hurting other people
to get the most beautiful woman or man you can have.  It's not worth it.  It won't
last.  It's great to have a relationship, but have it for the right reason.
Next.
If you have an anger problem
or get angry easily,
then imagine giving that person
something they would like to have.  This is called @maitre
@jampa
Love.
Imagine, try to remember how nice it is to give someone
something they like, something they want.
Try to have this attitude.
If you don't feel friendly towards another person,
then imagine what it would be like to meditate on
what it would be like to give them something they really like.
Next.
I'll give you a moment for this... I bet you don't remember what this is...
Tim cheats by looking ahead.
What was that?  It's
about pride.
Pride is also an obstacle to keeping vows.
And... one of the most common kinds of pride
in a monastic setting, where this book was generally taught,
is how much you know about the scriptures and how much data you have gathered
throughout your life.  I
really like that.  These Dharma teachings are very little known
and the more you collect them, the
more special you feel.
Pabongka Rinpoche said, "All the Dharma you have ever learned in your life, all the things you have memorized,
all the things you have debated,
all the Geshe degrees you could ever have,
compared to what is left to study... you know nothing."
You are like a worm at the bottom of the ocean,
which sometimes comes to the surface and looks at the stars.
Many of these stars have planets around them.
There are people on those planets.  There are things to know about these people.
Here are the things we know,
that we are so proud to know,
they are a tiny tiny [very] tiny fraction of what you could know.
So, don't be proud!
Next.
One of the great motivations for breaking your vows
or commitments, morality, that will stop you from reaching nirvana, that will stop you from reaching
the second level of Larm Rim -- personal nirvana --
is to understand emptiness, to study emptiness.
If you realize that the bad things
someone else does to you
come directly from what you did last week,
then you won't make big mistakes.  The more you study emptiness,
the more you study cause and effect, interdependence,
which means that that person comes from my seeds,
then the easier it will be for you to keep your vows.  It will be much easier for you.  So study, study, study!  I
had a very old Mongolian professor who had tuberculosis and
he would say,
"That's good. You're so proud, you have such a huge amount of pride from Princeton and
then the fact that you're a geshe,
it's a big help, a big help... You're
going to push yourself so hard
just to look smart.
That's luck, but later try to give it up.
Study how to be a good person. It's very funny.
On his deathbed, he gave me the text that Adam is translating. I
remember that. The
next one
Technically is that the fourth cause? No.
One of the causes of breaking vows or commitments
is that in the modern world it's very hard
to think about vows when you're so busy. When things are moving so fast.
There's a thousand things to look at on the internet
and life is moving so fast.
It's hard to keep your self-awareness. Am I
breaking my vows, doing things that hurt others?
I have to  slow down, go back to your vows.
And maintain a sense of awareness
that you have commitments not to hurt others.
The busier you are, the more mindful you need to be.
It's even easier to get annoyed with your partner when you're really busy.
He's trying to tell you something and
you have 10 things going on at work and...
"I don't have time to listen right now.  "My
boss gave me 10 things to do."
Those are the times when you need to slow down
and come back to your vows.
Don't forget your commitment to be nice to other people, even when you're
really stressed, really busy.
It's better to break a few business commitments than to
get angry and stressed and not be nice to people.
It's better to not pay a bill or miss a business meeting or
not give your best at work
if it means keeping your mind clear.
Next picture.
This is a lady buying something she doesn't need at the store.
See if you remember this story.
She said, "Oh, this box is so beautiful." She went to the store. She bought it...
...What's that home improvement store, the
place where you buy things for the home? Crate and Barrel.
She went to Crate and Barrel in America. She said, "Oh, my husband is going to love this box."  She
has no idea what she's going to use it for,
but she's going to buy it.
And when she gets home, her husband will say, "You're crazy, this is a worthless box."
"We have enough junk in the house."  "Take her back."  "Get your money back."
Should she go to the gas station and try to return it?
No, that's not where she got the box. It's obvious, but we have to say it.
If you buy a stupid box
because you like it and you think your husband will like it, which he won't...
and he convinces you to take the box back,
don't take it back somewhere else. Take it back to where you bought it.
What does that mean? You should
pay me.
When you have to confess
because you broke a vow,
try to go to the person who made you the vow.
Confess to the person who made you the vow.
Is it okay to confess alone at home?
No, for vows that you took from other people, generally.
If you didn't take a vow
from someone else, then maybe it's okay to confess at home,
confess in front of a Buddha statue or something. In extreme cases, it's okay.
But,  In general,
if you can go back to the person who made your vows
and confess openly, do it shamelessly. We act shamelessly all day long.
So be shameless when it comes to your vows, and say to yourself, "What the hell!"
Go straight to your teacher and say, "I broke this stupid vow."
And your teacher will say, "Wow, you're a really bad person."  You're like... "
Get over it and then you'll feel so clean, you'll feel so good.
You can be shy about a lot of things in your life, but don't be shy about your vows.
If you break a vow, go tell someone
and [that's] how you get rid of the... Get rid of the problem.
If you hide it from yourself and if you work harder to hide it than to confess it
or to keep your vow, then it's just stupid
and you're not going to feel good. You're not going to feel clean.
Be open with your teachers. I have this problem. I have this bad habit.
The karma is broken, the seed is broken.
Your teacher will say, "I've heard that before, you told me before." But be persistent and keep telling them.
Next picture:
It's about... Wait! Remember?
Again, it's about honoring the
little details of the vows.
It's actually  a vow for monks, they should brush their teeth,
with a stick called @SO SHING.
It was a stick that you have to use to clean your teeth. You
cut it out of a tree and you use it.
It's a toothbrush.
It's said that these monks should have their own toothbrushes and brush their teeth. It
might seem like a small thing.
"Wait, I'm trying to keep my tantric vow to go to Amitabha's paradise
and protect all living beings."  and Buddha says, "Yes, but in the meantime,
you could brush your teeth every day."
And you think that's not a very big vow.
But the little things build the Buddha's paradise.
They're the little things that bodhisattvas do
when they're kind to others.
Of course, everyone in this world...
...would stop a nuclear war or something like that if we could. It's obvious.
But, are you such a good person
that you wouldn't even want people to smell your breath
if it could hurt them?
If you're very careful
about the little things that could hurt others,
then we can say that you're maintaining your morality.
And then there are the little details that add the finishing touches
to your own Buddha's paradise, which you see in the next picture.
This person is decorating a Christmas tree.
If you've ever decorated a Christmas tree, and those of us who grew up in the Christian tradition,
our parents made us decorate the tree...
There's something special about
putting up the last ornament.
Everyone looks at the tree and says, "Is that  "Ready?" and they say, "Yes, it's ready."
He says, "Wait, there's something else we should add."
This ornament
is brushing your teeth. It's the little finishing touches
that you've added to your path to becoming a Buddha. The little things are what make a Buddha. It's
not the big things. It's not the big things. It's the attention
to the little details
of making other people happy that makes a Buddha.
Next.
See if you remember. I'll give you a hint - yamantaka.
It's a famous story from Lam Rim.
Monks and nuns are supposed to go to sojong [purification] twice a month and confess to each other the
mistakes they've made.
Openly.
The teacher said,
...I hit @?Gunty. ...I hit @?gunty,
a special piece of wood, it looks like a 2x4
and you hit it with another stick and it makes a sound. ...
It's a bell  ancient before metal was common. They
hit the board and when you hear the sound,
you have to go to sojong [purification]. They still do that.
I built one with my teacher. He wanted this kind of wood
and I made it to the right size.
There are a lot of rules....
When you hear the sound you
should... hold the board here
and hit it like this.
Then all the monks and nuns have to come and confess.
The teacher asked, "Did they hit the @gunty?"  "Let's go!"
Students say, "I'm not going to confess today."
The teacher says, "What?"
This is one of the main commitments of a monk, to go to sojong.
The teacher asked, "What are you talking about?"  The student replied, "I don't have to go today."
The teacher said, "What do you mean you don't have to go today?"
The student said, "Did you forget?  "You gave me a yamantaka initiation yesterday."
"I am Yamantaka, I am a Buddha."  "I don't need to go to sojong anymore."
The teacher grabs him by the ear and says, "What?  Are you Yamantaka?”
"Yamantaka is going to sojong with me right now."
This means: don't tell me that you are a great tantrika
and that you are above morality and
that you now have a greater vision.
That is a completely wrong idea!
If you have received a secret initiation
then you should go to sojong every morning. You
should go more than other people go.
Because that
gives strength to your tantric practice. Be kind to other people
and confess when you make a mistake.
Next.
This is a sad picture. We always think of morality as the roots of
our practice, the foundation of our practice.
Pabongka Rinpoche somehow reversed it.
This is a perfect picture.
He said, "Imagine an apple that
someone has cut in two."  Actually, he used a palm tree.
Someone cut off the top of the tree.
So you won't have any leaves. Not even
a single leaf will come out.
Therefore, you won't get flowers.
Therefore, you won't get the fruits that always come from flowers. You wo
n't get anything.
A person who is not nice to others day by day, hour by hour,
cuts off any chance
of getting those beautiful fruits of practice.
Next.
This was an idea of ​​something my teacher asked me...
Sorry, I asked my teacher, and I don't know if you remember, but I asked him.
The first of the five paths, the Path of Accumulation,
is reached when you have a personal tragedy.
But if you are on the bodhisattva path,
you reach it when you attain bodhichitta.
I said, "I don't understand what's tragic about bodhichitta."
And he said, "No, no, no."
"It's still a theme of tragedy.
It is the tragedy of every living being, every being in this entire universe
has the same tragedy.”
This common tragedy is the beginning of the five paths.
Thinking about that tragedy
is the beginning of the five paths for a bodhisattva.
So, really, it's the same thing.
The puppy is having a hard time, but now all the puppies in the basket are having a hard time.
We're all in this situation.
And that's the beginning of bodhichitta. The
next picture.
This is a guy shaking hands with someone in the office. I
imagine the lady is introducing them. This is Joe, he works in the advertising department,
and this is Sam, he works in the technical department. They're
shaking hands. Do you
remember what that is?
It was a really, really nice exercise where you close your eyes
and think of the person who irritates you the most.
And let's see if we can get angry. The problem with this kind of exercise
is that after about 10 minutes, you forget that it's an exercise. You
really get angry!
Let me see if I can get angry.
How are you going to do that? I'm going to
think of this guy who  It's been a tough week for me. "Okay, let it go."
Then, slowly, the person starts to tremble. You say, "What's happening?"
"I'm angry!" The experiment worked.
If your lama is there, he will say,
"Check how you feel when you start thinking about this person."
How do you feel? What comes to your heart? I do
n't know about you, but I have this little flutter in my heart.
I start to feel some kind of discomfort here or there
when I think about a person or an issue that bothers me.
I can intentionally generate tension
inside of me.
He says, "Let's do an exercise - try to trigger tension in your own heart,
and then look at that tension and acknowledge it, like you're shaking hands with someone."
Get to know how you feel
when a mental condition, a negative emotion
comes into your heart... and keep practicing it.
As soon as you feel better and forget about this person,
think about them again.
See if you can get angry again.
See if you can start getting angry again.
Try to get familiar with what you are feeling. Shake hands. "Hello. I am Geshe Michael."  Hello!
What's your name?" I
'm starting to get annoyed with this person.
"Nice to meet you."  "Now I know what you look like."
"Now I can forget you."  "I can avoid you in the future."
Next.
It's called visiting the center of the sun.
The theme of this Lam Rim was "Love in the Time of the Virus."
The virus is a big thing, it's spread all over the world.
I've lived a long life and I thought I'd seen it all.
I'm over 60 and I thought nothing new could happen.
"I'm pretty prepared for whatever happens."
"I've seen it all and nothing can upset me too much anymore."  Then this virus comes along and threatens us all in the world.
wow, this is a big thing, it's all over the planet. I do
n't know if it happened to you, but it did to me...
It's probably because of the negative seeds on principle 9, which is "bad intention",
to be happy when someone else has a problem.
When I heard that famous, annoying person got sick, I did
n't want them to die, but...
... "I told you it's bad to be bad."
And I found myself thinking this way. It
seems like a big thing.
It's like this problem has spread all over the planet.
For me, it's difficult to deal with.
We've just started,
after 10 years of studying Lam Rim, we've
just started studying the path of highly motivated people.
We're going to start that study
with the idea of ​​bodhichitta. What is bodhichitta? It
's not the enlightened mind. Forget that terrible, incredibly bad translation. It
's the wish that I can become a Buddha for  to help countless living beings.
There is a direct experience of this
in the same way that there is a direct experience of emptiness.
There are parallel experiences that we
have to reach in this life and again, we should do it in meditation.
We will describe an extraordinary... how to call it... revelation...
A borderline experience
that you reach when you are in a deep state of meditation.
Because time and space come from seeds,
if you mess with these seeds,
then you can compact time and space.
In a meditation that doesn't take more than half an hour
you could actually visit
every person in the universe
including animals and insects and birds and fish.
You could communicate with each one individually,
for half an hour.
You could make a commitment to each one of them.
You meet them, you see that each one is suffering,
each one has a difficult life and is worried about the future.
You could go to each one and say,
"I'll take care of it, relax."
I worked when I was at university.
I got a scholarship, but  I had to work a few hours a week.
It turned out to be 30 hours a week.
I had to drive a truck.
Actually, first they put me in a coffee shop and told me I was going to mop the floors... I
quit after 10 hours. I quit the first day.
Then they told me I could drive a truck. I was like, "Oh, that's cool!" "I'll drive a truck."
I drove a truck for five years.
There was this guy,
a permanent employee of the university, named Big John.
His name was Big John. A six-foot-tall Polish guy, huge.
Everyone was afraid
of him. They were afraid of him, but he was really nice.
He brought donuts to work and he was from Trenton, New Jersey. He
would do the best for us and cover for us if we needed it. One day, we wrecked a truck. We
hit a tree with the truck and it broke in two.
He  covered "Oh, the bolts weren't tightened properly
and I don't know what happened, the truck fell apart."  "Don't blame them."
"Don't blame these young people."
"All they did was drive the truck."
Then he winked at us and said, "I'll take care of you!" "I'll cover you." I
always think of him when I think of bodhichitta.
You'll meet every living being in the universe directly.
And you'll say, "Big John's got your back." "I've got your back."  "Don't worry."
"Don't worry!" "I support you."
That's bodhichitta. You should have that experience. You should
work for it. You have to meditate.
You have to study bodhichitta.
You have to study the Lam Rim on bodhichitta.
You have to do all these steps;
replacing self with others.
One day you will have that experience and you will meet every living being. You
will tell them, "I support you." "Don't worry."  "I'm backing you."
Big Mike is taking care of you or Big Tim or a Big Seiji.
"Don't worry."
"Don't stress."  "I'll take care of this!"  That's
exactly what it feels like. It's a personal commitment.
Why are we talking about it?
You're going to do this on countless worlds. When you do it, the day you do it, you're going to
do it on countless worlds.
An action that you commit to doing directly with every living creature in countless worlds
has no problem with some virus on one world.
It's nothing.
A virus that endangers
7 or 8 billion people is nothing compared to bodhichitta.
I said that if you spill ketchup on your shirt
and send the shirt into the middle of the sun, where it's 25 million degrees Fahrenheit, the
ketchup stain will probably disappear. You
probably don't have to worry about the ketchup stain. Work on your bodhichitta.
You'll destroy the virus, by the way, accidentally. It
's no big deal.
Next picture.
Don't mess with other paths.
Learn bodhichitta. Learn to have this experience.
Don't waste your time.
Don't focus on other things.  things. Focus on bodhichitta.
Then you don't have to do things twice.
I talked about doing things twice. This lady is in a hurry.
She says she doesn't have time for this bodhichitta stuff. I'm
going straight to tantra. You're still going to have to go
back and get that thing you forgot,
which is bodhichitta.
Work on bodhichitta first. You
don't have to go home, get bodhichitta, and then go back.
Then there was a radical example in the next picture.
It's hard to remember. I'll let you think about it for a second. I do
n't know if you remember.
It's a little complicated.
A group of 60 boys and girls were going to attain nirvana by directly perceiving emptiness,
which without bodhichitta, is lower nirvana.
Manjushri appears and teaches them about bodhichitta.
Maybe he taught them about this experience that I just talked about. They were all
irritated by Manjushri. They react in the "Don't waste our time!" mode.
"We are close to Nirvana." "We can feel it." "We can taste it."
"We have all already perceived emptiness, don't waste our time."
"Don't talk to us about this stuff."
Because they didn't follow the teaching of bodhichitta, they went
to hell. They did
n't reach Nirvana. They fell into the realms of hell.
But they burned away their negative karma
and became human again after many millions of years.
Somewhere deep inside them, this teaching that Manjushri gave them about bodhichitta remained, and they remembered it. They
became bodhisattvas and became Buddhas.
That would take less time than
reaching a lower nirvana without studying bodhichitta.
It would be faster to go to hell
and come back
and start over with bodhichitta
than if you didn't use bodhichitta
and went to a lower nirvana.
This is a picture of someone intentionally sending someone else down the wrong road.
This lady asks,
"Where is the highway to the store I want to visit?"
The guy knows the highway is blocked.
He says, "No.  Go there.  "The highway is blocked."  "Go to the other side."
And she insists: "No."
"Tell me where the highway I want is."
And he lies to her.
He says, "Take this path." Which is actually the long path that he wanted her to take.
This is a story about skillful means. The
next picture.
What you see here is the warm-up before running a race.
We usually use this image in connection with what? Remember?
It's a breathing meditation.
We usually say that the breathing meditation is just the warm-up. Don't think that it's the race itself.
In the Olympics, they don't have a competition for warm-ups before a race. There's no
such thing, you don't get a gold medal for warm-ups.
In this case, we're not talking about breathing meditation. We're talking about the
fact that it's good to follow the three main paths in order.
To be sad about this world.
To strive to have that bodhichitta experience directly.
To perceive emptiness so that you can help everyone.
Warm up first with feelings of sadness about  this life.
Next picture.
Almost done. I think we're very close. Are we close? Not that close. Okay. Do you
remember who these guys are? They're a really bad band.
I think you see them in malls or something, singing bad songs.
They're the "opening act."
The steps on the path for people with lower motivation
- who are trying to reach a higher rebirth - the
steps on the path for people with average motivation
- who are trying not to come back to this world -
the steps on the path for people with higher motivation
- these two levels are just the opening song. The
important thing is to reach bodhichitta. What's beyond bodhichitta?
There are the six perfections. We check:
The steps from the past that keep you going
and keep you out of the lower hells, the stages of the path to reach nirvana,
and then we have bodhichitta.
This experience of meeting every living being
and  to make a commitment that "I will take care of you."
Here is the sixth.
That's six in Chinese.
Here are the six perfections.
Now, which of these is the most important thing?
What is the real formation? What is the opening act?
These guys, obviously, the ones with lower nirvana, are not who knows what.
What is interesting, says Pabongka Rinpoche,
this experience
with every living being,
is the main act.
And that's what I want you to focus on.
I want you to try to have that experience.
If you have that experience, then we can talk about the six perfections
including number six, which is the perception of emptiness.
Let's talk about that later.
Come on, I want you to focus on having that experience.
By the way, a good way to have that experience is to imagine it and listen to the description of it.
Pretend you can do it and keep pretending.
Keep doing it.
It's like a slot machine.
I like to say, it's like a slot machine.
When you pull the lever,
it  they roll pictures;
cherries and things.
Not that I've ever played a slot machine... Well, once, with my dad.
You press the lever and then the picture discs spin like that.
Just imagine.
Your mother's face appears.
You say, "Mom, you look worried." She says, "Yeah, I'm worried about life."
You say, "Don't worry.  Big John supports you.'
"Calm down."  "I'll take care of this."
Then your father's picture appears.
Not just the image, but the person himself appears.
This is what it feels like in meditation.  Try to imagine.  Try to practice.
This will also trigger the real thing.
This will also trigger the real thing.  Bring each being forward, one by one.
See how they feel.  Make
a commitment.  "Don't worry."  "I support you."  "I'll take care of it..."
Then move on.  Bring another person.
Practice this way.  You can do this with five or six people.  It
will take less, because time will change.
Pabongka Rinpoche says this is the main show.
It's The Rolling Stones.  The
rest are new bands that aren't very good.  Who
is at the end?  Do they have an interpretation at the end?  Usually not.
Anyway, the rest leave the stadium... "Don't worry!".
Now we have gone over
the 10 interesting things about attaining bodhichitta.
We will only have time for the first of them in this Lam Rim.  The
first cool thing about attaining bodhichitta is...
if you were a nerdy kid
who played tennis in school,
your dream was to be on the tennis team.  The
next picture.
Yes, in the middle is Geshe Michael.
On top, not the weirdos below.
You can be on the team.  It's cool to be on the bodhisattva team.
Work to be on this team.
It's so cool to be on this team
because this team spans the [entire] universe.  It contains
all the good people in the entire universe.  It's nice to be part of this team.  It
's nice.
This was the first benefit of bodhichitta.  The
next picture.
This is a guy visiting an art museum.
He talked about the two levels of tantra: at the first level you meet angels,
at the second level you learn from them how to be an angel and how to become an angel.
At the first level we
should meet
real angels in person.  It's
not like sitting in an art museum and looking at a statue or a thangka of a person.
You meet the person directly and that's a completely different thing altogether.
If you try to practice tantra
without the experience of bodhichitta then it will be like looking at pictures of Buddha
instead of meeting Buddha.  They do
n't like talking to people who don't have bodhichitta.
They feel more comfortable
around people who have had this experience.  Try to have this experience
and then tantra will work for you.
If you don't have this experience,
Tantra will be difficult.  It will
be like looking at pictures of Buddha instead of sitting with Buddha.
Next.
If you try to practice tantra without bodhichitta, you may have bad results.  We
talked about the first nuclear test
in modern times.
Scientists have acknowledged that this explosion
could set off a fire across the world.
They were just trying to do something cool.
But they were risking a huge disaster.
This is tantra without bodhichitta.
It's like accidentally setting the entire sky on fire.  You'll screw it up.
Next.
Even small and neutral karmas
become powerful for a person with bodhichitta.
A person with bodhichitta can feed a bird,
say a prayer about it,
and it will affect millions of people.  He has this power.  The
next picture.
Even small evil deeds, such as stealing a fried potato to give to a bird, can be powerful if done by a bodhisattva.
But it's a dangerous practice.  We are not at that level.  We are not at that level.  We're not at that level.
Did you hear that?  Not?
I had a picture of
a fugu fish.
People in Japan, like macho guys, eat this kind of fish.
The fish has very poisonous parts that can kill you instantly.  In Japan, 50 people die every year from this.
But people continue to go to the restaurant.  To serve this fish in a restaurant
you need three years of special training, otherwise you will [surely] kill someone.  It's the
same thing when you steal a french fry to give to a bird,
because you want to help the bird.
We are not at that level.  Do not attempt to eat fugu fish unless you are trained.
Then we had a beautiful picture with Nick and Erin
and their big boss
who is Amalie [their daughter].
Amalie represents the Buddha,
and Nick
represents the father
who is bodhichitta, and Erin represents wisdom,
which is the direct perception of emptiness.
In a certain way,
somehow, I don't know if this belief is in Asia, but in a certain way the father is irreplaceable.
There's something special about the father.  I do
n't know exactly what it is.  But anyway...
Emptiness can be perceived on different levels,
in all three ways.
But for bodhichitta, you have to be a special person.  You
can only see it on the highest path.
It defines you
as a person on a higher path.
You need both to have the child who is the Buddha universe.  The
next picture.  Did I
say @?
Which Tim correctly identified today.
What is our main practice?   What is the number one thing in your life right now?
Until the next Lam Rim, the Lam Rim [called] "Buddha's Medicine"
...I want you to treat this as your main practice.
Try to have that experience of meeting countless living beings.
Try to have this experience.  I
don't care if you sit there for hour after hour and nothing happens,
just try, pretend.
Repeat it in your mind until the next Lam Rim.
Let's make a deal.  Make it your main practice.  The
next picture.
If this practice weren't so important then one of the greatest Buddhists of all time, Lord Atisha, wouldn't have sailed for
13 months at the risk of his life to obtain the teachings
on bodhichitta that you just received
in these videos. And you don't have to go anywhere.
If Atisha thought it was worth risking his life for 13 months
in a small ship
on the Pacific and Indian Oceans, then maybe it
's important, maybe it's valuable.  The
next picture.
I think the stupidest thing you can do in your life is go to Paris and not buy a croissant.  Okay
.  It's just a saying, there are probably other stupid things you can do in your life.
But for me the ultimate stupid thing
is to go to Paris and not go to a @?  At least
buy a pancake
on the street
with... What's that chocolate thing?
Nutella, yes.  [With Nutella.]
Not buying a pancake with Nutella...
Going to Paris and not buying a pancake with Nutella, then that proves you're crazy.
If you study Lam Rim,
if you've come this far in Lam Rim, and Geshela has been teaching it for 10 years,
eventually you reach the croissant,
which is the bodhisattva experience.
Don't be crazy to leave Paris without eating a croissant.  Don't leave Lam Rim without having this experience.
You would be an idiot.  I
finished with a croissant.  I think you want to give a presentation?
Not.  I was thinking there might be a croissant in that bag.
Tim Lowenhaupt
will make a formal presentation
to Geshela, my reward.
Oh, is it a @pande?  What is it called?
What is the name of that company?
Chocolate @Pande.  Here you need to divide it into three parts.
And give me all three, I mean no, just one.  I got the
panda chocolate.
This is what you give to your teacher when he teaches you about bodhichitta.
Let's make a deal.
For the next two months,
they are working on this experience.  Do Shantideva's dedication chapter in your meditation.
Try to work to have this experience.  The worst thing that can happen is that
you will at least plant seeds in your mind to have the experience.
Pretend.
Just sit down and imagine what that would be like.  Fantasies are good meditation.
Imagine that you had this experience of meeting
every living being, one by one.
Make a personal commitment to each of them
that you will take the utmost care of them.  Okay
.  See you in the next Lam Rim for "Buddha's Medicine".  Yeeeeeeeeeeeee!